Okay, so let's talk about the risk
management plan then.
Now, just like any
management plan, the risk
management plan is documenting procedures.
In this case, procedures regarding risk
management.
So again, just as a quick review,
remember you have the project management
plan, right, which is made up of the
subsidiary management plans as well as the
baseline, as well as those additional
components.
So one of the subsidiary management plans
is a risk management plan.
And just like any
management plan, the risk
management plan is documenting procedures.
How we're going to plan, execute, monitor
and control the risks on our project.
It does not actually contain the risks.
The risks are actually documented in the
risk register.
There's a separate video for that.
But it's documenting how, documenting
procedures.
And of course, iterative
approach, just like all of the
documents that we've been
discussing, as an iterative approach,
we're going to be
constantly making updicks.
Now, one of the key things to
understand about risk management
is that it starts right at
the inception of the project.
Even before we have a signed project
charter, we should start thinking about
how we're going to manage and control all
of the risks in our project.
And in fact, even the business
case may contain some risks,
right, or may contain some
risks that we've identified.
So this is not something that you just
start doing halfway through the project or
at a particular point in time of the
project.
No, this is something
that starts right at the
beginning, right, at the
inception of the project, right?
And remember, a risk is an uncertainty,
right?
So you're going to have uncertainty.
There's going to be a lot more
uncertainties at the beginning of the
project than the is towards end of the
project.
So risk management starts right at the
inception of the project.
And it continues throughout the project.
The risk management
plan, however, should be
essentially completed
as early as possible.
Now, when we say
completed as early as possible,
we don't mean that
it's done and that's it.
No, again, progressive elaboration,
iterative process, but we're constant
making updates as new information is
gathered.
It's just that very early on
in the project, we should
have a very good understanding
of how we're going to manage
and control all of the
risks in our project.
And obviously, the level
of involvement is going
to be based on the size
and nature of the project.
If you've got a very high risk project,
imagine, say, building a bridge between
two mountains spanning two different
countries.
That's obviously a huge major undertaking.
You're going to have many, many,
many vendors on a project like that.
And you've got two countries involved.
So obviously that's a huge undertaking
there.
There's going to be many, many risks that
you're going to be identifying.
So even before we start a project like
that, we're going to start thinking about
how we're going to manage and control all
of the risks on our project.
So some of the components then of the risk
management plan.
First of all, the methodology
and approach to risk management,
how are we going to manage
the risks in our project?
There are many different methodologies out
there for risk management, many different
approaches, different industries are going
to have their different approaches.
Some of you, for example,
may be familiar with something
called the failure mode and
effect analysis, FMEA or FAMIA.
That is a type of risk management.
Now, you don't necessarily need to know
FAMIA for the PMP exam, but I'm just
mentioning that if
you've come across that,
and then that is a type
of risk management.
type of risk management methodology.
So what's our approach to risk management?
That's all, how are we going to manage the
risks?
How are we going to identify risks on our
project?
That's all going to be documented here in
the risk management plan.
Plus who is going to be identifying risks,
who is responsible for risk.
But similar to how you have an issue
owner, you also have a risk owner as well.
So you're going to be identifying roles
and responsibilities.
Rolls and responsibilities for risks.
Potentially, a project, you
may have hundreds and
hundreds, maybe thousands
of risks on a project.
I like the project I just
mentioned, building a
bridge spanning two countries
between two mountains.
That's a huge major undertaking.
You're going to be
identifying hundreds, if not
thousands and thousands
of risks throughout the project.
Well, one person is not going to be
responsible for all of those risks.
So who is?
So how are we going to
identify risk owners and what's
their roles and responsibilities
and so on and so forth?
That's all going to be documented in the
risk management plan.
Now, based on that then, because
we've got thousands of risks,
we're going to come up with
different categories of risks.
we want to make sure then we understand we
manage all of these risks right so we may
create different risk categories right so
categories such as for example the
internal risk internal to our organization
external to our organization risk related
to technology risk related to government
standards right compliance and so and so
forth there may be many many different
risk categories and so different teams
will be responsible for
different risks Based on
that also, you may create
a risk breakdown structure.
Similar to a work breakdown structure, we
may end it with a risk
breakdown structure.
Now, many times when we are identifying
risk, we have to figure out, well,
how do we deal with the risk?
And in order to figure
out how to deal with
the risk, we have to prioritize our risk.
In order to prioritize our
risk, we have to figure out,
well, what's the probability
and impact of that risk?
So, how are we going to come up with the
probability and impact?
Sometimes, or a lot of times, you're going
to use arbitrary values like high,
medium low, scale of 1 to 10, or a red,
yellow, green type of classification.
But what does that mean?
Scale of 1 to 10, what does that mean?
High, medium low, what does that mean?
That needs to be defined.
So the definitions of probability and
impact need to be documented as well.
And where are they documented in the risk
management plan?
And then plus also things like timing of
risks.
How often are we going to be performing
the risk planning?
What kind of meetings are we going to
have?
How often are we going to have these risk
management meetings?
And in fact, generally how we going to
even identify risks and so and so forth?
How are we going to track the risk?
What's our tolerance limit?
Are we a risk-averse, risk-tolerant,
right?
Are we risk-seeking or risk-averse, you
know, so how are our stakeholders, right?
How are what's their approach to risk?
Plus things like budgeting.
How much money are we going to put in
contingency reserves for our risk?
How are we going to identify how much
money to put in contingency reserve, right?
And then how are we going to physically
put them in?
Does it need to be approved, for example?
So you may have a threshold amount where,
you know, if it's, less than a certain
amount, it doesn't need to be
approved, but anything above
that, we need to go through
the whole change control process.
So again, all of these need to be
understood as early as possible,
right, at the beginning of the project.
So risk management
should start right at the
beginning, right at the
inception of the project.
I'm very early on in the project,
we should have a very, very good
understanding of how
we are going to manage
and control all of the
risks in our project.
And they are all documented here in the
risk management plan.
Again, procedures, right?
It's not documenting the risks.
It's documenting procedures.
And documenting how we're going to manage
and control the risks on our project.
Okay.